is just really revealing of the way that
there is this intellectual and also
identity politics rot at the heart of
academia. What they had lumbered
themselves with was a cross between like
Ibram X Kendy and Jay from the
inbetweeners.
>> I would have the world and I'd have it
spinning on the saxis of love.
>> The asylum centers in Suta are
completely overwhelmed.
>> For the time being, Europe, I think, has
definitely passed this test. Every
single time that they try and put a lid
on this, the narrative just completely
falls apart. I think it's going to catch
up with any leaders who want to continue
to hold on to that sort of fantasy.
>> Hello and welcome to the Spike podcast.
I'm Fraser Myers and joining me down the
line today, we have Spikes editor, Tom
Slater.
>> Hello.
>> And from MCC Brussels, Jacob Reynolds.
>> Hi, thanks for having me. On the pod
today, we'll be discussing the
unraveling of Jason Arde, the Cambridge
professor, the crisis in Suta, and will
pay tribute to the late great Rod
Little. So, the Jason Ardeday affair has
kept us entertained for many, many
weeks. This is the Cambridge professor,
Cambridge's youngest ever black chair,
uh, who has now resigned following weeks
and weeks of accusations of plagiarism
and fabulism. Tom, do you want to take
us back to the beginning a little bit
for those people who haven't followed
the story with in as much detail and
with as much glee as as some of us may?
Yeah. No, I am a little bit sad that
it's over, at least in this current
period, because it has been the kind of
mother of all silly season stories. And
uh equal parts silly, absurd, and
sinister. I think it's fair to say. As
you say, Jason Arde made a lot of
headlines back in 2023 when he was
appointed at Cambridge University in the
sociology department as a professor in
the sociology of education. their
youngest black professor, aged just 37,
goes on this enormous media tour, guest
edits the Today program, gets profiled
on Good Morning America, and is
inspirational supposedly, not simply
because of his age, because he was a
young black professor, but also because
of his backstory. Um the fact that as he
tells it he because of autism and other
conditions wasn't able to speak until
aged 11 wasn't able to read or write
until 18. Miraculously seems to have
gone to university just two years after
having learned to read and write and
then very quickly climbs up the academic
ranks peddling if we're being honest a
kind of subteen vogue level of critical
race theory. You know inveing against
the racism of
>> Brit pop and home and away as Kathleen
Stalk has noted in Unheard recently. not
particularly good scholarship, dare I
say it. But then what was unearthed was
the fact that it wasn't just that the
scholarship wasn't any good, but some of
it might have allegedly been
plagiarized. Got to be a little bit
careful what we say cuz he's um loyed up
to his eyeballs still. But um the
telegraphers in the end found a hundred
passages from his PhD thesis which seem
to have been lifted or very lightly
changed from another PhD thesis from a
student at Brunell. And then came a lot
of scrutiny of his backstory. Uh not his
kind of neurode divergent origin story
which there's been not so much scrutiny
of but uh his long and illustrious CV
and list of extracurricular activities.
I mean he claimed that he'd run 30
marathons in something like 35 days. He
claimed to have raised a staggering 5.5
million pounds for charity. He claimed
to be on a television show, Seven Up,
that actually began 20 years before he
was born. I mean, you he might as well
have claimed to have, you know, beaten
the land speed record one rear of the
year four times and, you know,
translated all of Shakespeare into
playing on age nine. I mean, it was that
fantastical, shall we say? He has since
qualified some of those claims. I think
that the um more kind of shocking
element of this is that some of the
allegations that he's made about pretty
horrendous racist intimidation he claims
to have suffered has also, shall we say,
been called into question. There's a
fascinating and pretty devastating piece
in the Guardian of All Places which
looked at two claims in particular. One
of which was that a pig's head was left
at his parents' door in South London.
Arday claims that he reported this to
the police, that the police even found
the butcher from which the hog was
purchased. The Metropolitan Police have
no record of any such investigation
taking place. And he also claims that
whilst he was in post at Cambridge, he
was menaced by a masked man on two
occasions. The second time with a knife.
>> And yet it seems that he didn't report
this to the police. And also he didn't
mention it to any of his colleagues, nor
is there any CCTV footage to back up
what he was saying. So from top to
bottom, if if if these the critics turn
out to be true, this is kind of beyond
just Smlet levels of fantastical
storytelling, shall we say. Um and of
course naturally this was he was
originally defended on the grounds that
this was a essentially a racist smear
campaign. And I think it wasn't let's
just say I think it wasn't a coincidence
that his resignation coincided with
Cambridge and Jesus College where he
also had a post quietly opening
investigations into him finally having
dug in and defended him for so long. So,
at least this chapter of it of it is
over. But what a story it's been so far.
>> Well, well, yeah. And the cherry on the
cake is that some have accused his uh
resignation statement of being entirely
AI generated.
>> Yes.
>> Jacob, is there anything you want to
pick out of this scandal first of all?
>> Yeah. Well, I think it's kind of reveal
aside from being just hilarious at
times, it's kind of revealing, I think,
for two reasons. One is that it is in
kind of a good example of the fact that
there are throughout academia even at
the very highest reaches of academia
such as Cambridge or or elsewhere there
are people who anybody who has spent 5
minutes perusing the so-called academic
work that they produce has no right to
be in a prestigious academic setting and
is only there because there is this kind
of desperate desire to have people who
not just tick the ethnic boxes but in
this case tick the ideological box. It's
a thesis or a professor that's dedicated
to talking about all the DEI issues that
are of such such importance to our kind
of political and intellectual classes.
And so so he's there because not because
there's anything good about academia.
This is what drives people mad is you
see these distations that are published
by rep soal reputable scholars or
whatever. And the the quality of it is
just plain to anybody who's capable of
reading uh that this is not what was
once considered academia. So this is
he's like the epitome of of this of
someone who only exists because they
kind of flatter the prejudices of the
intellectual class. And then secondly
the the way in which the ethnic element
is very true there was obvious and even
the kind of there's even been outrage in
Cambridge University about the fact that
it was clear that this person was
appointed without any of the us even by
the kind of dodgy standards of academia.
even those academic standards weren't
met in the case of this appointment when
he when he finally got his prestigious
position at Cambridge. And it was only
because they were desperate to be able
to say, "We have the youngest black
professor, uh, the youngest black chair
and and so we can put him on the media
tour." And there's that cringe-worthy
video of him meeting one of the head
honchos at Cambridge University as it's
televised and her kind of melting into
the ground as she says how wonderful his
work was and how he's clearly the leader
of of in all fields that he's ever
attempted.
>> So good to see you.
>> It will be I think this is a tokenistic
appointment. What are your thoughts on
this?
>> We are so lucky to have you. Uh you are
the best in the world in terms of the
research that you do. They they loved
that little media tour and what it says
about academia in general is something
that many of us have suspected for a
long long time but is is just really
revealing of the way that there is this
intellectual and also kind of uh
identity politics rot at the heart of
academia and that's aside from this
being hilarious it's that that really
actually should be caused for worry.
>> Absolutely. Um, Hillary Kreman is the
woman in the in the video and you know
that's his his boss or was his boss
until um a few days ago and I mean the
gushing is incredible. I mean her exact
words are you are the best in the world
at what you do and you know on the one
hand um this is probably
>> it could be true because everyone in
this field is is full of frankly
>> and also you know her specialtity um
interesting enough is looking into it.
Um she is is on poetry and peace and how
you know essentially embedding poetry
into various um you know educational
curricula can bring us to a more
peaceful world. So I'm not convinced
that her research is is is topnotch
either. Um Tom, what do you want to add?
>> No, just following on from what Jacob
was saying, I think that the question is
not how did it get this far. Um in terms
of Jason Arde, the question is not um
why did an individual, if the
allegations are true, choose to make up
so many things, plagiarize so many
things, embellish so many things?
Because you do just get fraudsters and
fabulists and fantasists from time to
time. That's nothing new. But it was the
extent to which he was indulged. I mean,
why did it take so long for Cambridge
either to notice or at least accept that
what they had lumbered themselves with
was a cross between like Ibram X Kendy
and Jay from the Inbetweeners, you know,
at least in the Inbetweeners, no one
actually believed Jay when he said he
was, you know, he got knocked off at the
school play and once knocked a cow out
with one punch, apart from, you know,
Neil. But like this is the thing like
how even though so much of this was so
blatant, so much of it was outlandish.
You go back and watch some of those
interviews and in real time you see
Christian and Guru Mirthly or other
people kind of saying, "But how did you
do this tremendous feat of sporting
prowess or whatever it might be?"
>> You know, I I went to university at 20,
but I had the reading age of a
9-year-old, you know? So, you're you're
trying to really kind of
>> really I mean, is that possible?
>> Yeah, it is.
>> Implicit in the whole woke capture of
universities is a lowering of academic
standards. they have embied this deeply
racist frankly idea that if you hold
ethnic minority students or academics to
the standards that they would expect of
anyone else that it's impossible for
them to succeed. Um, and I suppose the
other thing is the extent to which just
identitarian thinking just infects
entire disciplines now to the point
where even though his scholarship wasn't
really up to much. If you're in a world
in which just subjectivity is praised
above all else in which hearing the rage
of the supposed sub alton is the point
of academia and politics then the extent
to which the work is coherent,
interesting, even original kind of falls
by the wayside to a certain extent. So
it's just the extent to which when left
unchecked identity politics just
corrupts the entire institution. you end
up throwing out what was supposed to be
the the the entire purpose of the
university in terms of academic
excellence and merit and what have you
in pursuit of other goals. This kind of
mystical racial identitarian reckoning
that appointing someone like this is
supposed to help you along the way
towards. Um but you know it's tempting
at times like this to say that we sort
of almost ultimately feel sorry for him.
You you've seen a lot of that in the
coverage and I get it to some degree.
He's a kind of prisoner of his own um
decisions to a certain extent and the
environment in which he's allowed to
thrive. But I've got to say I've got a
lot more sympathy for
>> first of all the people who were smeared
just for calling him out. I mean there
are now two reports of a journalist and
an academic who had the police called on
them for harassment for poking around
his uh questionable citations. Shall we
say
>> a 4 months investigation? Why was that
necessary? Commissioner,
>> we dropped the ball on that one. Let's
not sort of beat about the bush. Um
there's also the the other black
academics who never asked to be
represented by this man and probably
were much more deserving of
professorship than he was um who been
kind of smeared by association. And also
if you just think about you know the
students the young academics who are
having to make their way through these
institutions at the moment you know
being told off in seminars for using
pronouns wrong. Meanwhile this guy is
kind of peacocking around campus. So you
put all of that together and it just
shows how rotten a lot of these
institutions have have become and it's
uh become an enabler for figures like
this and that is something that they're
going to have to reckon with one would
hope.
>> Absolutely. And and it goes well beyond
academia and the media are complicit in
this as well. I mean uh Arday was
profiled by the BBC channel 4. He's
appeared on Question Time. He appeared
on Good Morning America. So you know the
US their hands aren't clean. And of
course, he's uh got a memoir coming out
next week which bizarrely hasn't been
pulped. It's is still, you know, it's
still coming out. Um there's been some
some people have managed to get their
hands on it and have picked up some
extra tall tales. I mean, there's
>> stuff about him being in a coma um for a
while, you know, claims that he
>> he's a really unlucky fellow.
>> Very unlucky. I mean, it's both he he
kind of like has these sort of
superhuman talents and then just these
extreme almost like mythical levels of
uh bad luck. Um so he's he's been in a
coma. He had he had um I think he had to
have brain surgery just before his his
his viviveror uh which wiped out much of
his memory. There's one story that
really caught my eye in it, which is
essentially that he was um mugged and
beaten so badly as a teenager that he it
gave him epilepsy. But by sheer
coincidence um the people who attacked
him would ended up becoming his students
when he was um doing some teaching work
at a London university um when they
realized that they were, you know, that
they knew each other. Um and they
discovered that Jason Aard had so
magnanimously decided that he didn't
want them to go to prison. They were
moved by this and they decided to turn
their lives around. Uh and they now
coach at risk youth and one of them has
asked Jason Aard to um be his the
godfather to his his child. So a very
you know very heartwarming story. You
can see why
people would like to be brought along by
this but you do wonder why people didn't
ask more questions. Jacob, anything more
to add? Yeah, asking questions is one
thing, but if anything to go by the kind
of the the response inside Cambridge,
which should be really the moment for a
little watershed moment or the thinking
seriously about how far these kind of
DEI inspired policies have have gone. It
doesn't seem to be the mood inside
Cambridge. I note today as we're
recording this there's a a letter
circulating from some academics at
Cambridge who are complaining that the
main problem with all this is the
so-called quote tide of racism that it
is unleashed which is especially
interesting when you consider that
previously questioning any of his claims
would have been labeled immediately as
racist. So what they're really saying is
not that this is a problem because it's
been kind of unmasked. is a problem
because it makes everybody look bad and
it undermines all of the all of the
issues that they'd like to push. And so
what should be the moment for a little
bit of cleaning up of house inside
Cambridge and more broadly in academia
in fact you have all these academics
doubling down on it in the remarkably in
the same way that all of our uh
political and intellectual class handle
things which is never the problem is
never that there was a problem. The
problem is that all these nasty
right-wing people, all these racists,
whatever, are suddenly using it to their
advantage. And it's amazing the degree
to which even these Cambridge academics
managed to fall back on the exact same
kind of identification of the problem
that we see everywhere else. It's
fascinating as well like the way the
goalposts have shifted so many times.
Like originally it was like how dare you
accuse him of plagiarism. Now the line
from kind of Kind Andrews and others is
that um yeah maybe there's a bit of
plagiarism but all academics do that and
you would never have looked into him if
he wasn't black. I mean you can tell
that they're on the back foot that they
keep having to shift the goalpost and um
I mean it's it's the complete inverse of
the truth. I mean again if these
allegations are true he was allowed to
thrive despite a lot of question marks
over his academic credentials and his
backstory precisely because of race
precisely because of skin color combined
with ideology in the way that Jacob was
saying because if he was a young black
academic who happened to have dissenting
views shall we say on multiculturalism
or race relations or what have you
imagine we he would have got that
position to begin with. So yeah, it's
it's amazing how even in the face of
this evidence, people can just continue
to cry racism. It's this it's precisely
that way of thinking that got Cambridge
into this mess in the first place.
>> Should we talk about Suta? Um last week
the Spanish enclave of Suta in North
Africa was overwhelmed when 60,000 um
migrants tried to cross the border from
Morocco. Um the line of the Spanish
government, Jacob, is that this is all
sorted. Um, everyone has been either
voluntarily left the enclave or has been
pushed back uh into Morocco. There's
nothing to see here, nothing to worry
about. Um, do you buy that line? Yeah, I
I think it's remarkable and indeed
outrageous that this has become the
story and the story not just of the uh
the Spanish authorities but of the the
EU as well in general and also of plenty
of uh the media figures uh that have
kind of latched on to this because for
one it's hardly as if this was kind of
no big deal. the fact that a few that
people have gone home after engaging in
one of the kind of largest and most
brazen acts of border violation that
that that we've seen in in recent years
that that the fact that that can just
happen is worthy of serious reflection
in and of itself. The degree to which
the that the this kind of the Spanish
state was almost complicit in inviting
these people in. All of that desperately
needs to be analyzed. And then and then
at the same time it doesn't appear to be
the case at all that uh that everybody
has simply returned home and that the
Spanish authorities have quickly rounded
up everybody affected. Indeed most of
the on the ground reports that you read
suggest that there's anywhere is
probably changing by the day but there's
anywhere uh up to kind of 5,000 migrants
still remaining. Most of them seem to be
actually not Moroccan citizens, but
people from other parts of of Africa and
subsaharan Africa that came over at the
same time of all these uh of all the
Moroccans. And this is because the
Moroccans are now refusing to receive
back the people who aren't Moroccans.
So, in a way, this almost seems like a a
convenient way in which the the Moroccan
authorities kind of dispersed themselves
of a load of potentially problematic
people that they they didn't want anyway
under the cover of some mass violation
by the Moroccans. And you got this this
like relatively tiny area where there
are now 5,000 people have no right to be
there by if you look at some of the
videos still coming out literally I mean
it sounds like overblown but literally
roaming the streets looking for in some
cases trouble but at the very least
looking for food and shelter a large
number of uh ch unaccompanied children
among them although given how we know
that the EU struggles to distinguish
between a genuine child migrant and
someone who's got a full-blown beard uh
we might be skeptical some of those
claims. Um but and and then finally the
the whole thing that was kind of the
back stop of this narrative around
around this instant was that oh whilst
this might be a breach of Spain's
territorial integrity, don't worry
because nobody's going to make it to the
mainland, right? Even though this area
is actually technically part of the the
Shen zone that they've kind of tried to
maintain this as the as the key thing,
just don't worry, we're going to keep
them all there at the very least and
they won't make it into Europe proper.
But then again, this narrative is also
falling apart. the because of the fact
that the asylum uh the asylum centers in
Suta are completely overwhelmed, they've
already begun the process of
transferring people who were in those
asylum centers to the mainland. And
whether these are people who came during
the mass breakin or people who've
wandered across at various points in in
in the past months and years doesn't
matter because the point is this has
resulted in a net transfer of people to
the European mainland who have no right
to be there. So every single time that
the they try and put a lid on this the
the kind of European and Spanish
political elite every single time they
try and put a lid on it the narrative
just completely falls apart and there's
a huge degree of both outright
falsification and then an attempt to
manage the narrative of well that is
really really disastrous and we need to
get into as well what this really tells
us about the the EU's border and the
degree to which this as I said at the
beginning is very much invited in by the
by the whole uh institutional and legal
apparatus that has defined EU border
security for quite some time.
>> Yeah. And and you know, this comes off
the back of Spain uh regularizing what
it expected to be about 500,000 um uh
illegal migrants. Um in the end, it's
turned out to be um you know, 1.2
million or or thereabouts. Um there's
also been you know, Spanish court
decisions that have said that um anyone
who arrives by sea, by swimming um can't
be pushed back. And I think that was
something that seems to have uh
instigated this particular surge. And
Tom, as Jacob says, you know, people are
being invited to come regardless of
whether you know, regardless of how many
people have been returned on this
occasion. No,
>> I think that's right. And of course, the
immediate spark for this was, as you
say, this Supreme Court ruling in Spain,
as well as a lot of questions about the
extent to which the Moroccan authorities
allowed it to take place. Ongoing
disputes about the status of Western
Sahara, this kind of breakaway
territory, the politics of that have
been sparked for previous incursions,
not nearly on this scale, but there was
one in 2021, if I remember correctly,
about 5,000 people made it over the
border. So, those are the kind of
immediate um sparks for the shocking
scenes that we saw last week. But
there's al also the broader context and
I think when Pedro Sanchez first
announced this effective kind of amnesty
for illegal migrants you wrote a piece
for spikes razor talking about how this
feels like it could be another v
shaffendas moment the point in 2015
where angler Merkel heighted the Syrian
migration crisis just essentially
invited them to come to Germany we'll
manage we'll sort this out and then
unleashing all kinds of disorder and
political ramifications that are
continuing to be felt in Germany and
across Europe And what you see is this
kind of kind of whiplash that takes
place. the other country like Spain and
a country like Germany which will
posture which will kind of throw open
the borders in one way shape or form and
then when they're confronted with the
consequences of their own virtue
signaling suddenly have to do things
which are from their perspective quite
murky in the ca in the case of sutor
sending in the army and the navy and the
police to try and get on top of this
issue or of course in the case of 2015
and everything that happened after that
angler Merkel and the EU having to go
captain to wretched tighter one in
Turkey chucking billions of euros in
order to house Syrian migrants and also
in the process kind of handing him
tremendous leverage in his dealings with
the EU because at any point he could
threaten to unleash another migration
wave on Europe. Um, so it's one of those
things where you see this kind of
tremendous whiplash that takes place
sometimes in response to just the
staggering material consequences of
their sort of open borders virtue
signaling, but also I think just
understandable backlash for the public
who are suddenly confronted with, as I
say, the ramifications of what it is
that their leaders have been doing. and
and especially with a country like Spain
like of course Pedro Sanchez is imposed
but he was elected last time around I
believe on a kind of reduced mandate a
reduced majority this policy seems to be
largely speaking a kind of soap to the
radical left part of his coalition
meanwhile Spain like many other
countries is roing on the issue of
illegal and legal mass migration in
which by looking at polls at least kind
of 60% of the country thinks the numbers
are far too high um and is carrying on
regardless is carrying on the last 10
years haven't happened. Um, it's caught
up with him now and I think it's going
to he's it's caught up with him now and
I think it's going to catch up with any
leaders who want to continue to hold on
to that sort of fantasy um even in the
even with the plentiful evidence of
their own eyes showing what terrible
consequences can be brought there of
>> and and and finally Jacob I mean of
course the problem here is that you know
it's it's not as if um the decisions
that made by Pedro Sanchez only affect
Spain because we have the European Union
um essentially Every country is beholden
to the border policy of the I guess the
the country with the freest. Um you know
Sanchez has opened Europe's border uh
not just Spain's border. And you know if
you're in if you're in Poland and you're
not happy about this you can't vote him
out.
>> Indeed. And I mean this is one of the I
think that the two major consequences of
of this but it's been brewing for a
while is the the the shenhen zone the
free movement zone or passportless zone
uh which applies to most of the the
mainland EU. Uh that is seriously being
called into question. We've seen the
Italian government take measures to
reintroduce border checks, but this is
something that only kind of builds on
the precedent that's already been
established by other countries such as
Germany and Austria, reintroducing some
forms of passport control on the
mainland precisely because I mean
Sanchez is radical in his kind of pro-
migration rhetoric and and policym to a
degree that even embarrasses most of the
other promigrant kind of European elite.
So he's he's a especially radical thing,
but he is in fact calling into question
the entire uh kind of architecture of of
of of the EU migration policy by simply
drawing attention in particularly
outlandish fashion to how mad the
consequences of these of of these
policies are. So the whole Shenhen area,
the passportless travel that we were
repeatedly told was the kind of the kind
of uh glory end goal of of the European
Union, that dream is being seriously uh
called into question. And also the other
thing I think that that really needs
some attention and we talked about this
on on our podcast and have a few times
is the degree to which the policy of the
European Union who are deeply deeply
uncomfortable with enforcing border
control their policy has always been to
outsource the control of borders to
other countries to third countries like
Morocco like Turkey uh etc. And what
this and and they do that because they
are uncomfortable enforcing the border.
They don't want to be the ones doing the
push backs or or turning people around
or deporting people. If far prefer that
uh kind of dodgy strong men in in other
parts of the world as they would see are
doing this. But that just means that in
the last analysis the European Union is
entirely beholden to these countries who
can weaponize it at a moment's notice.
And the European Union has completely
lost the ability to actually control its
borders by pretending this is just a
problem that can be managed by someone
else. And I mean we do see in the
European Union some small crawling moves
towards uh getting more serious again
about border security. And there are uh
there is an emerging kind of coalition
in the even in the European Parliament
uh which is passing various bits of
legislation to make deporting people uh
easier and trying to give greater powers
to uh to border authorities. But this is
going to take an awful long time to
unravel when the kind of entire
direction and architecture of the
European Union for so long has been
entirely devoted to either pretending
that borders aren't a problem or
demonizing anybody who tried to enforce
their borders as we saw in the case of
Poland and Hungary who were the subject
of attacks and fines and and all kinds
of legal weapons by the European Union
simply for enforcing their borders. And
so I think this is might be the
beginning of a little bit of a change in
rhetoric by EU elites, but it's going to
take a long long time and it's
definitely not going to be the kind of
work of EU elites like Ursula
Vanderlayan who actually put an end to
this. But when you do have more
sovereignty-minded national leaders in
place to some degree as we see with
George Maloney, but uh but increasingly
will be the case elsewhere. Is it going
to be n up to national leaders to kind
of capitalize on what is now I think
undeniable consensus in in European
politics that this era of borderlessness
just can't continue.
So the great Rod Little, the spectator
and Times columnist and Times radio
presenter uh died this week age 66.
Tom, do you want to say um a few words
in honor of the great man?
>> I mean so much has been said already. I
mean, the outpouring of not just
condolences, but affection and reverence
for Rod um was to be expected because of
all that he achieved, all that he meant
to a couple of generations now, I think,
of writers
>> and readers. It's hard to add to that. I
mean,
>> you you feel like you're reaching for
the same old pearlist, but I think he
was poundforound Britain's greatest
political columnist. you know, in a kind
of sea of like boiler plate pros, a lot
of kind of wonkish, boring writing about
politics. He he was uniquely sort of
writerly and provocative funny, which is
such a kind of rare quality these days.
And he was also a tremendous friend of
Spike for many, many years. You know,
would always be up for events, would
always appear on a podcast, tremendously
supportive of us as an organization and
as writers, always kind of forthcoming
with with help and advice and what have
you. Um, but I I do just kind of go back
to just the quality of the work itself.
I mean, it's it's no exaggeration to say
that he was a sort of singular figure in
British journalism, somebody who was
genuinely laugh out loud funny. And you
can measure how good he was and how
interesting he was and how brilliant he
was in his capacity for upsetting all of
the right people. We've seen a lot of
those kind of quotes from previous
columns being recycled used to damn him
in his absence. having to remind people
that, you know, when he said things
like, "I couldn't be a school teacher
because I wouldn't be able to stop
myself from shagging the kids," that was
obviously a joke. People don't seem to
be aware that this thing is a joke. Um,
and it was, yeah, it was that
combination. His writing could be on the
one hand tremendously kind of literary
and um, creative, but also wonderfully
crude and blunt when it came to going
after his particular target. So, it's
it's a tremendous loss, definitely. But
I think you certainly see the measure of
the man in the plaudits which have been
rolled out for him and also just the the
kind of personal stories of what what a
basically good and supportive bloke he
was in so many other respects. So RIP
definitely
>> absolutely and and as you say you know
it has been the exactly the most uh
humilous and um annoying people.
I mean, you know, Owen Jones, Medi
Hassan, you know, I dare I name anyone
else, you know, those are those are the
people who who've reacted um most
weirdly and most, you know, spitefully
to his his death, which is completely
unsurprising. Um, Jacob, anything any
thoughts?
>> Yeah. Yeah. Well, I think that the one
of the many things that was really
interesting about him was this political
journey that he himself had been on from
being just such a kind of person with
relatively mainstream political views
kind of like the BBC way of looking at
things for lack of a better phrase and
then finding himself as so many people
not just of of his age but of variety of
generations did suddenly kind of
confounded dumbfounded by the modern
world and the the crazy turn that
politics had had taken and that the the
culture had taken. And so finding that
you you don't feel that you yourself
have changed, but the world around you
has suddenly gone mad. And he
communicated that sense really really
perfectly and and and hilariously. Um
and and and also I mean he was still
kind of doing this from as it were
beyond the grave because I mean one of
my favorite interactions of the whole
thing was when Jeremy Vine I think made
some tribute to him and immediately
somebody then replied to Jeremy Fine and
Jeremy Vine was forced to then take on
the fact that Rod Little has said that
we should install grotting wire to take
out the cyclists and it was like still
and you could just that you him over the
internet squirming and so the fact that
he's still doing this from beyond the
grave is is really quite impressive.
And and then finally, I just a little
bit like uh whenever the passing of a
major figure like this, you just think
that this was a very particularly
British kind of person, British kind of
writer. He embodied so many of those
classical British virtues that we like
to think of in terms of the quality of
the pros, the ability to be funny,
refusing to be pigeonholed. Those it's
like a it's a kind of this is why it's
not just a kind of moment for people who
care about uh commentary writing, but a
genuine kind of moment of of British
history in a way, a passing of of an era
in a sense, because he embodied, I
think, so many of those things that we
like to think on our best days are the
markers of of of fine British people.
>> Thank you, Tom. Thank you, Jacob. Um,
but that's not all. We're about to go
over to Spike podcast unlocked where
we're going to discuss the potential
reproshit.
But before that, uh, Jacob, do you want
to tell people about the academy which
is a brilliant event that is coming up?
Yeah. So, I uh, one of the things I do
is I convene this event. The academy is
an annual intellectual kind of retreat
where we take one of the the big
intellectual themes of our times and
kind of probe it through intellectual
history and literature. It's a
tremendous amount of fun for up. It's a
kind of perfect event for anybody who's,
as I said earlier, confounded by the
modern world, but wants to understand
kind of what the roots of this all are.
We've got a load of great uh speakers
including Tim Black of Spikes, who's
going to talk about uh the emerging uh
Islamism and third worldism. We've got
writers that spiked people will be very
familiar with from Lola Salem to Chris
Bis. Um and and the the theme this year
is uh hollow leviathan. The idea that
the state is increasingly kind of devoid
of all authority, but at the same time
is capable of in incredible acts of
authoritarianism. So if you fancy a
little weekend away in in in the
countryside around Bedfordshire, it's a
fantastic time for you. You'll be
surrounded by like-minded people. It's
going to be the 21st to 23rd of August.
go to the Ideas Matter website uh to
find out more and I'm sure we'll put it
in the in the comments or in the notes.
>> Absolutely. Yeah. Find find the link
below and and get your tickets.
>> The Labour Party, a bit like the
Democrats, is on a journey from from
having been the party which was supposed
to represent the working class to being
a party which actually represents
tossers. Yeah, if I could put it like
that.
Thank you so much for watching the Spike
Podcast. We'll be back next week, so
make sure you subscribe to the channel
and click the bell so you never miss an
episode. If you enjoyed the Spike
podcast, then why not check out what
else our channel has to offer, from our
documentaries to our weekly interviews
and podcasts like the Brendan O'Neal
Show. And if you're a Spike supporter,
you can watch the second half of this
episode by logging in on the Spiked
website. If you're not yet a Spike
supporter, then why not sign up now?
You'll get unlimited access to the
website, add free reading, discounted
tickets to our events, and so much more.
So, become a Spike supporter today by
going to spikedonline.com/support.
That's spikedonline.com/support.